Clark Music Company Records
Clark Music Company Records
1889-1960
Clark Music Company (Syracuse, N.Y.)
24.5 linear ft.
Records of the musical instrument retail business in Syracuse, New York; founded in 1889. Correspondence (1889-1960); memoranda (1921-1960); and merchandising and financial records (1894-1960), including bank statements, inventories, ledgers, price lists and catalogs, repairs records, and marketing information.
149729
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers of the Clark Music Company are the records of the retail trade in musical instruments and materials which was carried on from 1889 to 1960 by a family-owned firm in Syracuse, N.Y. Melville Clark (1883-1953) managed the company for many years, lending to the business his considerable fame as a harpist and musical inventor and collector. This collection contains material on the changing musical tastes of America over a span of seventy-one years, as well as information on the development of modern techniques of advertising and selling. The papers date from 1889 to 1960, with the bulk falling in the years after 1900. They have been organized in four sections: Correspondence, Memoranda, Merchandising and Financial Records, and Miscellany.
Correspondence (boxes 1-24), which dates from 1889 to 1960, has been arranged chronologically by year and month. One important correspondent was Thomas Mott Osborne, noted prison reformer from Auburn, N.Y. His letters date from 1910 to 1915. Osborne's interests as an amateur musician led to his acquaintance with Melville Clark, and various members of the Osborne family purchased a considerable amount of stock in the firm. The correspondence generally provides a wide-ranging description of the business contacts and methods of operation of Clark Music.
The Memoranda (boxes 24-25) date from the last years of the 1950's. These have also been arranged chronologically. They relate primarily to problems of internal company organization and management.
The Merchandising and Financial Records section (boxes 25-30), dating from 1894 to 1960, contains all manner of material on musical instruments and their sale, as well as financial records of company operations. This section contains colorful detail on player pianos, harps and talking-machines, as well as the first radio and television. Of special interest are the subsections on advertising and sales promotions, which provide information on the development of modern marketing methods. Also included are: bank statements, records, dealership agreements, guarantees, inventories, ledgers, personnel records, price lists and catalogs, repairs records, shipping and receiving registers and time purchasing contracts. The materials are arranged chronologically within each subsection.
Miscellany (boxes 30-31), 1893-1958, contains various types of ephemera which are related largely to musicians, concerts, and social events. There is also some biographical material on the Clark family, as well as assorted newspapers, magazines, clippings and separates.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Music; New York State; Clark Music Company (Syracuse, N.Y.) -- Archives.; Clark Music Company (Syracuse, N.Y.) -- Records and correspondence.; Music -- 20th century.; Music trade -- New York (State) -- Syracuse.; Musical instruments -- Manufacturers' catalogs.; Musical instruments -- Marketing.; Bank statements.; Correspondence.; Inventories.; Ledgers (account books); Memorandums.; Price lists.; Sales catalogs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mrs. Dorothy Clark, July 1965
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1893-1900, 14 folders (Box 1)
  - 1901-1906, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - 1907 General [undated], Jan-May, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - 1907, Jun-Dec, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - 1908 General [undated], Jan-Feb, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - 1908, Mar-Dec, 10 folders (Box 4)
  - 1909 General [undated], Jan-Mar, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - 1909, Apr-Dec, 9 folders (Box 5)
  - 1910 General [undated], Jan-Mar, 4 folders (Box 5)
  - 1910, Apr-Sep, 6 folders (Box 6)
  - 1910, Oct-Dec, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - 1911 General [undated], Jan-Apr, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - 1911, May-Nov, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - 1911, Dec (Box 9)
  - 1912 General [undated], Jan-Nov, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - 1912, Dec (Box 10)
  - 1913 General [undated], Jan-Oct, 1 folder (Box 10)
  - 1913, Nov-Dec, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - 1914, General [undated], Jan-Sep, 10 folders (Box 11)
  - 1914, Oct-Dec, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - 1915 General [undated], Jan-Jul, 8 folders (Box 12)
  - 1915, Aug-Dec, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - 1916 General [undated], Jan-Apr, 5 folders (Box 13)
  - 1916, May-Dec, 8 folders (Box 14)
  - 1917 General [undated], Jan-Apr, 5 folders (Box 14)
  - 1917, May-Dec, 8 folders (Box 15)
  - 1918-1920, 5 folders (Box 15)
  - 1921-1924, 4 folders (Box 16)
  - 1925 General [undated], Jan-Sep, 10 folders (Box 16)
  - 1925, Oct-Dec, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - 1926-1930, 6 folders (Box 17)
  - 1935 (Box 17)
  - 1939 (Box 17)
  - 1941 (Box 17)
  - 1942 General [undated], Jan-Jun, 7 folders (Box 17)
  - 1942, Jul-Dec, 6 folders (Box 18)
  - 1943-1946, 5 folders (Box 18)
  - 1947 General [undated], Jan-Jun, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - 1947, Jul-Dec, 6 folders (Box 19)
  - 1948-1950, General [undated], 5 folders (Box 19)
  - 1950, Jan-Dec, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - 1951-1955, 6 folders (Box 20)
  - 1956, Jan-Jun (Box 20)
  - 1956, Jul-Dec (Box 21)
  - 1957 General [undated], Jan-Jul, 8 folders (Box 21)
  - 1957, Aug-Dec, 5 folders (Box 22)
  - 1958 General [undated], Jan-Apr, 5 folders (Box 22)
  - 1958, May-Dec, 8 folders (Box 23)
  - 1959 General [undated], Jan-Jun, 7 folders (Box 23)
  - 1959, Jul-Dec, 6 folders (Box 24)
  - 1960 (Box 24)
- Memoranda
  - [General], Undated (Box 24)
  - [General], 1921-1955; 6 folders (Box 24)
  - [General], 1956-1960; 5 folders (Box 25)
- Merchandising and financial records
  - Advertising
    - Budgets and costs, 1906-1959 (Box 25)
    - Contracts and agreements, 1906-1959 (Box 25)
    - Copy, undated (Box 25)
    - Cuts and flyers, undated; 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Cuts and flyers, Undated (Box 26)
    - Cuts and flyers, 1895-1956 (Box 26)
  - Bank statements, 1906-1959 (Box 26)
  - Bids and proposals, 1924-1959 (Box 26)
  - Cash books, unbound
    - General, 1947-1949 (Oversize 1)
    - Sundry charges, 1947-1948 (Oversize 1)
  - Credit and collections, 1907-1960; 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Dealership agreements, 1897-1957 (Box 26)
  - Guarantees, 1894-1916 (Box 26)
  - Inventories, 1959 (Box 26)
  - Ledgers, unbound
    - General, 1928-1937 (Oversize 2)
    - General, 1948, Jan-May (Oversize 3)
    - General, 1948, Jun-Oct (Oversize 4)
    - General, 1949 (Oversize 5)
    - Accounts payable, 1946-1947 (Oversize 6)
    - Accounts payable, 1947-1948 (Oversize 7)
    - Accounts payable, 1948 (Oversize 8)
    - Accounts payable, 1949 (Oversize 9)
    - Accounts payable, 1950-1951 (Oversize 9)
    - Profit and loss, 1928-1937 (Oversize 10)
  - Personnel
    - Miscellaneous, 1953-1959 (Box 27)
    - Applications, 1905-1959 (Box 27)
    - Appointments and duties, 1913-1950 (Box 27)
    - Expense accounts, 1958-1960 (Box 27)
    - Reports, 1916-1929 (Box 27)
  - Price lists and catalogs
    - undated (Box 27)
    - 1893-1960, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Repairs
    - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
    - Shop reports, 1957-1958; 6 folders (Box 28)
  - Sales promotions
    - Miscellaneous, 1911-1959 (Box 28)
    - Developmental plans, 1910-1918 (Box 29)
    - Form letters, undated (Box 29)
    - List of prospects, 1916; undated; 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Securities, 1907 (Box 29)
  - Shipping and receiving
    - Goods in and out books, 1941-1945 (Oversize 11)
    - Goods in and out books, 1945-1947 (Oversize 12)
    - Goods in and out books, 1953 (Oversize 10)
    - Receiving book (vol. 1), 1957-1959 (Box 29)
    - Receiving book, records and sheet music (vol. 2), 1951-1952 (Box 29)
    - Shipping book (vol. 3), 1957-1959 (Box 29)
  - Statistics, 1911-1959 (Box 30)
  - Time purchasing contracts, 1897-1959; 5 folders (Box 30)
- Miscellany
  - American Guild of Banjoists, Mandolinists and Guitarists, 1915-1916 (Box 30)
  - Biographical material, Clark family, 1922-1949 (Box 30)
  - Ephemera
    - Miscellaneous, 1904-1946 (Box 31)
    - Concerts and social events, 1898-1958 (Box 31)
    - Musicians, 1906-1950 (Box 31)
  - Magazines, Symphony Notes, 1945-1946; 5 issues (Box 31)
  - Magazine separates, 1908-1922 (Box 31)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1893-1929 (Box 31)
  - Newspapers and magazines, 1901-1907 (Box 31)